I
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): mean, a lot of people go to jail. Few write books. How did you how did you do that? It's a great story. So believe it
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): or not, when I go to jail. Right. How old are you? Oh, it's just that I was 41 years old, 42. Yeah, it's a terrible time to go to jail. Right. I lost everything. Right. And I got two kids at the time. Yeah, which was breaking the news to them was the most heartbreaking thing ever. I mean, like, literally, it was like too much crying. And then, you know, I still get emotional about it. Right. I bet. And.
had to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): tell them like you know daddy made mistakes and now he's in the hysterical they were 11 and nine at the time right so um i go to jail and it's not the worst jail in the world not worried about slipping in the shower so it's like a minimum security
Speaker 4: but jail sucks right who's my bunkmate tommy chong from cheech and chong what was he doing there so he's there for selling not marijuana but bongs bongs it was the most ridiculous thing ever so he's doing a year in a a year and a day for selling bonds. I'm like, shit,
he's doing a year and a day
Speaker 4: day for bonds i should probably get 3 000 years how long did how long are you serving i had 22 months yeah right so he's there for a year and a day and you know the first few days you know there's not much to just tell each other stories and i'm telling him stories about my life the insanity and did you know who he was of course yeah they put us together we shared us we shared a cell yeah because they were both high profile so they just put us
Speaker 7: together right so they could watch us both at once right
Speaker 8: so in jail as in normal life all
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the famous people know each other basically right so and he's a great he's a great guy and he was he was writing a book at
Speaker 4: the time and
Speaker 4: And I'm telling him stories and he's just rolling his laughing hysterically every night. Right. And the third night he's like, you know, I thought you were making this shit up. But my wife Googled you. And it's like all true. In fact, your assistant knows you from her father from back in the day, he was a friend of mine, right? He's like, this is you actually sank the boat. You crashed these cars. You did all this insane. You made all this money and all these drugs was you have to write a book. And I'm like, really?
Speaker 4: You think my life's exciting? Like, because it's your life. No matter how crazy your life is, it's yours. You don't think, right? You think it's just normal. I'm like, he's like, I'm Tommy Chong. I think your life is just insane. He goes, write a book. So I started trying to write and I was a terrible writer. Terrible. I couldn't write anything. I'd never written before like that. You know? So after like a month, I'm like, oh, this is just not working. I go to the prison library and I stumble upon a book called Bonfire of the Vanities by Tom Wolfe. Of course. I pick up this book and I'm like,
my
Speaker 4: god I want to write like this so I plowed through the book and then I started with the yellow highlight and I used this book like a textbook and I taught myself to write by modeling Tom Wolfe so it's like I had a model now and I spent about three months just every I mean every metaphor how we use grab how you describe locations how you use conflict and I really start to see my writing dramatically improve so I wrote about a hundred pages when I was in jail and then
Speaker 4: I ripped them up, I didn't think they were good enough. I got out of jail with no pages, but I had a skill now, right? So when I got out, I was like, you know, I don't know what to do with my life. And I was like, maybe I'll just start trying to write again, right?
So I
Speaker 4: wrote about 12 pages and I'm like, wow, I think those are really good. I thought they were pretty good. I hate my own writing always, right? It's like when you write, it's very,
like you
Speaker 4: always hate what you write, right? So I'm like, I think this is pretty good. I sent it to a few friends and they're like laughing, like, oh my God, it's the funny, I'm like, really?
So I
Speaker 4: sent it to a book agent I knew very casually, Just a casual friend, right?
Speaker 4: So I call him and say, I want to, you know, write a book. He goes, oh great, let's get you a ghostwriter. I said, well, I want to write it myself. He goes, can you write? I'm like, I'll send you the pages. I sent him 12 pages. Next day, he calls me back. He goes, did you pay Tom Wolfe to write those pages? It was like that close to Tom Wolfe's voice, my first draft, right? I'm like, no, no, I wrote it myself. He's like, it's really good. He goes like, write 10 more pages. So I said, all right. So it took about a week to write 10 more pages. I wrote another 10 pages. I sent him the pages. 15 minutes later, he calls. She goes, "Stop everything you're doing.
Speaker 4: You have no idea what's about to happen to your life. This book is going to be a master head master. I'm going to get a movie made about this. We're going to get Leo DiCaprio to play you, right? I mean, right from the start, right? I was like, I thought he was delusional, right? But I didn't have much going on back then, right? So I was like, screw it. So I hold up and literally I had a little tiny apartment and I spent one year.
Speaker 4: Just like doing 18 hours a day, writing the book, the Wolf of Wall Street, right? About on page 60, he took it down to Random House, we bought the book, I got a nice advance to like at least live, right? And then when the book was finished about a year later, went through seven edits, because I overrode it, got it from 1000 pages down to 500 pages. And then when it was still a manuscript, it became a bidding war between Brad Pitt and Leo DiCaprio.
Speaker 4: Yes, it wasn't a book. Yes. I know it's crazy. Right. And then, you know, Leo brought in Scorsese and I would love Leo. So I sold to Leo and Scorsese after a nice bidding war. And so began, you know, the story of the Wolf of Wall Street. What happened with the movie? And then there was a delay, by the way, for five years, because that was 2007. And then the writer strike hit and it got delayed.
Speaker 4: which ended up being a great thing and this is really empowering for all the listeners I'll tell you why because when I when they wrote the script when the script was done by a guy named Terry Winter who adopted the book he did an incredible job the first draft of the script was amazing right but it ended with me in jail like because I went to jail and got out right and that was the ending of the movie of the script right there was this delay then for four years after the writer's strike
And
Speaker 4: during those four years, I got very wealthy again, going out there and speaking and training entrepreneurs and teaching sales, right? So finally, four years later when Leo called me because we're ready to go, he came back to my new house. I was living in a mansion on the water. He's like, what the hell happened to you? Like in four years, I was in a tiny apartment now into a very nice house again. And like, oh, I'm doing this stuff around the world. I showed him my clips from live on stage. He's like, wait till Marty sees this. He's gonna go crazy. They rewrote the third act of the movie and made it a comeback
Speaker 9: story.
Speaker 9: So that's, yes, I kind of rewrote my life story. When
Speaker 10: were you happier at the peak of your success, pre-conviction
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): or on the comeback? Comeback. I was never happy before. Why? Number one, I was a massive drug
Speaker 12: addiction. Yeah. Like I'm literally massive drug addiction. What were you using? Quaaludes and cocaine. Quaaludes? Quaaludes, yeah. Is this the 70s? 70s. Well, you know, I... Where'd you get Quaaludes? I'll tell you how. So we, when I got really wealthy, you know, they made them illegal in the United States. Yeah. Right? Like a long time ago. I'm
not.
Speaker 12: But in
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): Switzerland and Italy and Spain, we were going country to country and like buying out the pharmacies of all the ludes from overseas and bringing them back into the United States. Not to sell them, just to take them, just to eat them all. We weren't dealing them, just consuming massive quantities of these quaaludes, right? And I got so wildly, I was taking about 10, 12 a day. You get very deep. Yeah, yeah. And like one of them would knock out a
Speaker 18: 200 pound Navy SEAL for eight hours. I would take four and walk around. So what was the appeal of that?
you
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): know um euphoria the incredibly euphoric they get this like first you get this tingle phase and then you get like the slurs and the happy drool phase and anyway it's incredibly
Speaker 19: euphoric and then i said well what's the drool phase the drool
Speaker 12: phase is when you're like drooling as you're talking but you're like
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): well drooling's not a big deal baby's drool you know and when you're slurring like baby slur i slur it's always a justification but then the problem is is the fourth phase is unconscious. That's great.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): That's the best justification for though is is unconsciousness, which is a problem. So what do you do then?
Speaker 20: Well, a responsible drug act will then take cocaine to make sure you don't go to work. Right. So I started to balance it out. The
Speaker 22: yin and the yang. Come on cocaine, which is great work. Great. The problem is cocaine makes you anxious. So I needed Xanax to
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): get rid of the anxiety.
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): Right. So I take Xanax to call the anxiety, but I still need something to kick me over the edge with sleeping. So I took some ambient to sleep and then some morphine for the pain I had. And before I knew it, I was taking
Speaker 22: 22 drugs at the same time. I was like a human petri dish. Right. And I was just incredibly high all the time. I know I'm very lucky. I know I don't you know, I always wonder why I didn't have any permanent damage. Yeah, right. I think most of it was not a big drinker.
and I
Speaker 22: think alcohol is like that wild card.
- Alcohol
Speaker 23: and Quaaludes
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): will kill you. - Yeah, it's a wild card, it's like gasoline on the fire. So I was very fortunate, I got sober in '97. - How? - Went to rehab, I went to rehab, I got sober.
Speaker 24: - What's withdrawal like from Quaaludes?
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): - Not bad, it wasn't that bad. You know, for me it wasn't so much withdrawal was the problem, it was more like just, I needed like an adult time out. I was so done with it. Like I think, you know, people can get sober in rehab,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): people can get sober in the rooms of alcoholics anonymous right you can get sober anywhere but you have to be ready to get sober yeah if you're not ready right you could be in the world's greatest rehab and you'll just relapse you'll run it you'll climb over the wall as soon as you got you'll use again i was done i i was like my life was so out of control i had my
Speaker 22: kids were starting to get older now they're four and five years old so i was like i gotta end this so i know i was very happy to stop using
drugs
Y'all
Speaker 26: hear people say the news is full of wine and Kennedy's motorcade.
Speaker 27: 239 female cell death of Jeffrey Epstein.